Guide to the Irving Emery Gray Papers, 1915 - 1980 UA.29.02.0035
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Irving Emery Gray papers
1915-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gray, Irving E. (Irving Emery), 1897-1980
UA.29.02.0035
12 Linear Feet
Irving Emery Gray (1897-1980) was chair of the Zoology Department at Duke University and helped establish the Duke University Marine Laboratory in Beaufort, North Carolina. His interests included marine zoology and ecology, and biological adaptation. The Irving Emery Gray Papers include correspondence, reports, notes, documents, slides, photographs, and other materials about Gray's personal and professional life. Major subjects include the Zoology Department at Duke, marine biology, Arthur Sperry Pearse, and the National Science Foundation. English.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Irving Emery Gray Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1961 (A61-306), 1971 (A71-72), 1972 (A72-61), 1974 (A74-113), 1975 (A75-165), 1979 (A79-92), 1983 (A83-104), and and 1998 (A98-68).
Biographical Note
Irving Emery Gray was born on May 23, 1897, in Providence, Rhode Island. He received a BA from the University of Massachusetts in 1921, followed by an MS and Ph.D. from the University of Wisconsin. Gray came to Duke in 1931 after holding positions at De Pauw and Tulane. His specialty was the adaptation and ecology of marine life. He helped to develop the Duke University Marine Laboratory in Beaufort, North Carolina, and served as its Acting Director in 1955-1956. He also served as the chair of the Department of Zoology from 1940 to 1956. Gray served on the advisory committees of a number of marine research centers, and was a member of many professional societies. He died in Durham in 1980.
Collection Overview
The collection includes correspondence, reports, notes, documents, slides, photographs, and other materials related to the professional career and personal life of Gray. His interests in education, zoology, biology, and ecology are represented. The collection features materials generated by his work as chair of the Zoology Department, records of the Duke University Marine Laboratory, copies of Gray's printed works, and correspondence with colleages. The first series, Personal and Family, contains correspondence and other materials related to Gray's personal life. The next series, Publications, Abstracts, and Other Writings, includes both Gray's own publications as well as those of his students. The third series, Zoology Department, Duke University, includes correspondence, minutes, memos and other materials related to Gray's administration of the department. The next series, Correspondence - Personal, Professional, contains correspondence arranged by both individual names and group affiliations. The Course Materials series documents the courses Gray taught, while the next series, Duke University Marine Laboratory - Beaufort, NC, documents Gray's work to establish a research laboratory. The following series, Lists, Keys, Charts, Graphs, Checklists, Bibliographies, includes a variety of reference materials. Field Trips contains notes and other information from Gray's research excursions, and Research Notes and Papers (Titled Folders) features the research used for Gray's publications. The following series, Research Notes and Papers (Unsorted) contains similar materials, but is unprocessed. The final series, Photographic Materials (Positives, Negatives, Slides) contains photographic material related to Gray's personal and professional life.
Related Material
Marine Laboratory Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Dept. of Zoology records
Duke University Archives
Arthur Sperry Pearse Papers, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Photographs; Slides (photographs); Adaptation, Biological; Marine animals -- North Carolina -- Beaufort; Marine biology; Marine ecology; Zoology -- North Carolina; Duke University. Department of Zoology; Duke University. Marine Laboratory; Gray, Irving E. (Irving Emery), 1897-1980; National Science Foundation (U.S.); Gray, Irving E. (Irving Emery), 1897-1980; Pearse, A. S. (Arthur Sperry), 1877-1956
- Personal and Family
  - Clippings, 1927-1969 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - George M. Gray [father], 1932-1946 (Box 1)
  - Gray, George M. - Publications, 1932-1946 and undated (Box 1)
  - Gray, Virginia - Obituaries, 1964, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Journals in Personal Possession of IEG, ca. 1967 (Box 1)
  - Lists - IEG Students (M.A., Ph.D.) (Box 1)
  - Maps of Photographic Tours, undated (Box 1)
  - Marine Biological Atlas, 1970-1976 (Box 1)
  - Massachusetts Agricultural College - Graduation and Alumni Activities, 1921-1971 and undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1919-1970 and undated (Box 1)
  - Obituaries (IEG), 1980 (Box 1)
  - Poems by IEG, A.S. Pearse, and Anonymous, ca. 1930-1950 and undated (Box 1)
  - Publishing Contracts, 1937-1956 (Box 1)
  - Retirement, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Retirement - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Vitae and Lists of Publications, ca. 1962-1976 and undated (Box 1)
- Publications, Abstracts, and Other Writings
  - Abstracts, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Lectures, Papers, Miscellaneous, 1963-1971 and undated (Box 1)
  - Obituaries, 1957-1967 and undated (Box 1)
  - Publications [by IEG and students], 1926-1972 (Box 1)
  - Unpublished manuscripts
    - "Feeding Rates of the Seastar... ," 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Introducation to the Benthic Ecology of Estuaries," undated (Box 1)
    - "The Major Coastal Communities of NC," 1968 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous untitled manuscripts, ca. 1968-1969, [2 folders] (Box 1)
- Zoology Department, Duke University
  - General Files
    - Budgets - RESTRICTED, 1941-1957 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, C.S. Brimley to Bert Cunningham, 1925-1927 (Box 1)
    - Curricula and Courses, 1949-1968 and undated (Box 1)
    - Faculty Grants and Proposals
      - Progress Reports, 1954-1962 (Box 1)
      - Progress Reports, ca. 1952-1956 and undated, [2 folders] (Box 1)
    - Faculty - Miscellaneous, 1941-1958 and undated (Box 1)
    - Faculty - Research, 1959-1962 and undated (Box 1)
    - General Departmental, ca. 1944-1967 and undated (Box 1)
    - Graduate Studies Director, undated (Box 1)
    - Honors, 1956 and undated (Box 1)
    - Journal Club, 1942-1952 and undated (Box 1)
    - Lists - Graduate Students, Staff, Award Recipients, Alumni, Faculty - RESTRICTED, 1928-1971 and undated (Box 1)
    - Long-Range Planning Committee, Ten Year Projection for, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Minutes - Dept. Meetings, ca. 1940-1960 (Box 2)
    - Nursing Curriculum, 1945 (Box 2)
    - Retiring Faculty, undated (Box 2)
    - Science and Mathematics, Laboratory Conference for Teachers of, ca. 1954 (Box 2)
    - World War II, Zoo Dept. in, ca. 1940-1949 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Individual Files
    - Bailey, Joseph R., 1946 (Box 2)
    - Hall, F.G., 1965, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Howell, Thelma, 1954 (Box 2)
    - Johnson, M.W., 1950 (Box 2)
    - Nace, George W., 1949-1956 (Box 2)
    - Odum, Howard, 1953-1955 (Box 2)
    - Sandeen, Muriel I., 1950 (Box 2)
    - Schmidt-Nielsen, Bodil, 1953-1955 and undated (Box 2)
    - Vernherg, John, 1951, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Ward, Calvin, 1952-1956 (Box 2)
  - Individual File - Arthur Sperry Pearse
    - Biography, Obituaries, 1940-1960 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - 1917-1953 and undated (Box 2)
      - Letters on ASP's 70th birthday, 1947 (Box 2)
      - Illness and Death, 1953-1960 and undated (Box 2)
    - Pearse Memorial Committee, 1957-1964 and undated (Box 2)
    - Poems by and about ASP, ca. 1947-1953 and undated (Box 2)
    - Writings, 1928-1953 and undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence - Department Chairman - Chronological, September 1940-September 1956 and undated, [6 folders] (Box 2)
  - Correspondence - Department Chairman - Alphabetical
    - Alumni, 1954-1955 and undated (Box 2)
    - Alumni and Students in Wartime, 1941-1945 (Box 2)
    - Evaluations - General Departmental - RESTRICTED, 1942-1956 (Box 2)
    - Evans, F. Gaynor, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Gross, Paul M. - RESTRICTED, 1947-1956 (Box 2)
    - Jones, Sara, 1945 (Box 2)
    - Summer Session, 1947-1955 (Box 2)
    - Wenger, Karl, 1953-1954 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and Memoranda, Departmental - Reflections on the Zoology Department - RESTRICTED, 1962-1966 (Box 2)
- Correspondence - Personal, Professional
  - Chronological and No Date
    - 1921-1958, [3 folders] (Box 2)
    - 1959-1977, [5 folders] (Box 3)
    - Letter with Message Found in Drift Bottle (from Experminet on Currents), August 1968 (Box 3)
    - Undated letters (Box 3)
  - Alphabetical by Person
    - Allevein, J., 1964-1967 (Box 3)
    - Barnes, Robert D., 1953-1973 (Box 3)
    - Berry, James, 1960-1969 (Box 3)
    - Carter, William, 1959-1973 (Box 3)
    - Cerame-Vivas, Maximo, 1961-1969, [2 folders] (Box 3)
    - Cerame-Vivas, Maximo - Copper Mining in Puerto Rico, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
    - Culver, Starr, 1958-1968 (Box 3)
    - Davis, Donald M., 1966-1968 (Box 3)
    - Davis, Huckett, 1958-1969, [2 folders] (Box 3)
    - Godfrey, Melinda, 1967-1969 (Box 3)
    - Grassle, J. Fred, 1964-1967 (Box 3)
    - Hall, F.G., 1930-1944 (Box 3)
    - Howard, Kenneth, 1965 (Box 3)
    - Hutchison, Victor, 1955-1970 (Box 3)
    - Kirby-Smith, John, 1955 (Box 3)
    - Knight, C.B., 1954-1961 (Box 3)
    - Krause, J.B., 1940-1955 and undated (Box 3)
    - McCloskey, Lawrence R., 1960-1971 and undated, [2 folders] (Box 3)
    - Maturo, Frank, 1956-1969 (Box 3)
    - Potts, Mary, 1964-1968 (Box 3)
    - Roberts, Henry S., 1940-1974 (Box 3)
    - Robertson, Clyde H., 1954-1961 and undated (Box 3)
    - Scarboro, Betty P., 1963-1966 (Box 3)
    - Schmitt, Waldo, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Schultz, George, 1960-1968 and undated (Box 3)
    - Strasburg, Donald, 1953-1955 (Box 3)
    - Wainwright, Stephen, 1956-1963 (Box 3)
    - Wegener, Barbara, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Wells, Harry, 1953-1967, [2 folders] (Box 3)
    - Willmon, Karl, 1948-1971 (Box 3)
    - Wirtenson, Mary E., 1962-1966 (Box 3)
  - Alphabetical by Organization, Project, Event, etc.
    - Estuarine Study Project, 1968-1970, [2 folders] (Box 4)
    - Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Grants and Grant Proposals
      - Atomic Energy Commission, 1952-1956 (Box 4)
      - Duke University Research Council, 1935-1971 (Box 4)
      - Estuarine and Oceanic Bottom Communities, 1957 (Box 4)
      - Office of Naval Research, 1948-1956 (Box 4)
      - U.S. Department of Commerce - US Coast and Geodetic Survey, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Hatteras Cape - US Department of Interior - National Park Service Corespondence, 1957-1964 (Box 4)
    - Institute of Fisheries Research, 1949-1951 and undated (Box 4)
    - Lenal Bottom Conference, 1956 (Box 4)
    - National Science Divisional Committee, 1935 (Box 4)
    - NC Academy of Science, 1947-1966 (Box 4)
    - NC Wesleyan College, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Puerto Rico, Univ. of - Visiting Professor, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - Research Program Statements - General, 1944, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Society for the Study of Evolution, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Southern Association for the Advancement of Science, 1941-1942 (Box 4)
    - Woods Hole Marine Biological Lab, 1942-1962 (Box 4)
  - National Science Foundation
    - Conference on Distribution of Specimens, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and Other Papers, 1956-1968 (Box 4)
    - Evalutions of Other Proposals, 1963-1965 (Box 4)
    - Grant Proposals, 1957-1965 (Box 4)
    - Grants Progress Reports, 1959-1967 (Box 4)
    - Institutes for Science and Math Teachers, 1952-1957 (Box 4)
    - Radiation Biology Course for Teachers (with Atomic Energy Commission, 1956-1957, [3 folders] (Box 4)
    - Undergraduate Research Participation Awards, 19637, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Undergraduate Research Participation Award - Susan Carol Adams, 1971 (Box 4)
- Course Materials
  - Ecological Distribution of Marine Animals, 1963 and undated (Box 4)
  - Laboratory Directions for Bryozoa, ca. 1940 (Box 4)
  - Lectures
    - Biotic Communities, undated (Box 4)
    - Ecosystem, undated (Box 4)
    - Ocean, 1957-1958 and undated (Box 4)
  - Plankton - Ocean, 1963 and undated (Box 4)
  - Research Problems, undated (Box 4)
  - Teaching and Lab Guides, 1910, 1933-1936 (Box 4)
  - Test Questions, Notes, etc., 1931 and undated (Box 4)
  - Zoology 12, undated (Box 4)
  - Zoology 203 - Marine Ecology, Misc., ca. 1949-1958, [5 folders] (Box 4)
  - Zoology 225-226 - Field Zoology (Box 4)
  - Zoology 341 - Historical Zoology, 1952 and undated, [2 folders] (Box 4)
  - Zoology 355 - Marine Benthic Ecology, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Zoology 355 - Marine Dimertebnate Zoology, 1963 (Box 4)
- Duke University Marine Laboratory - Beaufort, NC
  - Administration, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Clippings, ca. 1938-1967 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports, 1938-1971 (Box 4)
  - Eastward: Design, Dedication, Cruises, Other Papers (Box 4)
  - Eastward: Research Facility Requests, 1957-1967 (Box 4)
  - Evaluations - Thoughts on DUML by IEG - RESTRICTED, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee - Minutes and Other Papers, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee - Great Lakes Colleges Association Cooperative Program, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Grades - RESTRICTED, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Grant Proposal - Cooperative Research and Training Program in Biological Oceanography at DUML, 1961 (Box 5)
  - Gray Building Dedication, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Hatteras Project, undated (Box 5)
  - Hatteras Project Publications, 1960-1967 (Box 5)
  - Humorous, undated (Box 5)
  - Lists - Graduates, Class Lists, Candidates, Personnel, 1929-1967 (Box 5)
  - Long Range Planning, 1958-1961 (Box 5)
  - Manpower Symposium, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1964 and undated (Box 5)
  - Printed Matter - Bulletins, Booklets, 1939-1974 (Box 5)
  - Proposals and Projects - Courses and Facilities, 1961-1963 (Box 5)
  - Publications - Bibliography, 1939-1961 (Box 5)
  - Publications - DUML-related, 1957-1967, [7 folders] (Box 5)
  - Radiation Biology Course, 1953-1960 (Box 5)
  - Reference Collection, ca. 1968-1972 (Box 5)
  - Southern Regional Education Board - Regional Program for Marine Sciences, 1952 (Box 5)
  - Taxonomy, Specialists in Marine, 1967 (Box 5)
- Lists, Keys, Charts, Graphs, Checklists, Bibliographies
  - Amphibians and Reptiles of NC (Box 5)
  - Asteroidea of NC, [2 folders] (Box 5)
  - Bibliography - References, History (Box 5)
  - Checklist (Box 5)
  - Checklist of Common Marine Animals of Beaufort, NC (Box 5)
  - Checklist - Ecology I, II, III, [3 folders] (Box 5)
  - Checklist - Invertebrates, 1953, [2 folders] (Box 5)
  - Checklist - Marine Invertebrates (Box 5)
  - Climatographic, 1957 (Box 5)
  - Crustacea of Beaufort (Box 5)
  - Durham Spiders (Box 5)
  - Distribution Maps - NC (Box 5)
  - Gastropod Genera of Beaufort, NC (Box 5)
  - Keys
    - to Amphibians and Reptiles (Box 5)
    - to Beaufort Amphipods (Box 5)
    - to Hausterid Amphipods of NC (Box 5)
    - to Hydromedusae of Beaufort (Box 5)
    - to Polychaete Families (Box 5)
    - to Polychaetes of Woods Hole (Box 5)
    - to Freshwater Fishes of NC (Box 5)
  - List of Marine Fishes and Fish-like Vertebrates of NC (Box 5)
  - Lists of NC Animals, [2 folders] (Box 5)
  - Lists, Species (Box 5)
  - Maps (Box 5)
  - Maps, Beaufort (Box 5)
  - Maps, Distribution of NC Amphibians and Reptiles (Box 5)
  - Marine Gastropods of Beaufort (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Molluska of NC (Box 6)
  - Mud Crabs of Chesapeake Bay (Box 6)
  - North American Distribution of Mutabilia found in NC (Box 6)
  - Pelecypoda of Beaufort (Box 6)
  - Stomatopods of NC (Box 6)
- Field Trips
  - Chronological, 1933-1935, 1955-1967, [18 folders] (Box 6)
  - By Location or Type
    - Bogue Sound - Dredging, 1955-1967 (Box 6)
    - Bottom Hand - Highway St., 1958-1959 (Box 6)
    - Cruises, ca. 1965-1966 (Box 6)
    - Eastward Cruise, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Lake Michie, 1960-1962 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 6)
    - New Hope Creek - Hollow Rock, ca. 1949-1959 (Box 6)
    - Old Reservoir - Eno River, ca. 1951-1963 (Box 6)
    - Piney Mountain Pond, ca. 1953-1967 (Box 6)
    - Plankton, 1959-1963 (Box 6)
    - Shackleford Banks, 1955-1967 (Box 6)
    - Soil Fanna, 1951-1962 (Box 6)
    - Travel - Offshore, 1955-1967 (Box 6)
    - Travel - River, 1955-1967 (Box 6)
- Research Notes and Papers (Titled Folders)
  - Brief Study of the Blood in Triturus Viridescens (Box 6)
  - Commercial Crabs of Chaetopterus (Box 6)
  - Commensalism (Box 6)
  - Comparative Anatomy, [2 folders] (Box 6)
  - Eggs, Dehydrated (Box 6)
  - Embryologists, Articles on (Box 6)
  - Linuhus, [4 folders] (Box 6)
  - Problems (Box 6)
  - Profile: Hatteras, N.C. March 4-5, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Profile: Lookout, September 14, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Sand Dollar Data (Box 6)
  - Scallop Data (Box 6)
- Research Notes and Papers (Unsorted)
  - Unsorted research notes and papers (Box 6-7)
- Photographic Materials (Positives, Negatives, Slides)
  - Large Card File Box (Positives and Negatives)
    - Sailing and other ships, ca. 1920-1929 (Box 8)
    - Sharks and other fish, undated (Box 8)
    - Snakes and Insects, undated (Box 8)
    - Collecting - on boat, shore, etc., undated (Box 8)
    - People - many unidentified, 1922-1926 (Box 8)
    - Maryland (Shore), undated (Box 8)
    - Louisiana (New Orleans, etc.), undated (Box 8)
    - Waveland, Mississippi, 1928 (Box 8)
    - Greater Boston, undated (Box 8)
    - Mt. Vernon and unidentified, undated (Box 8)
    - Key West, 1915 (Box 8)
    - Woods Hole, Mass (includes Marine Biological Lab, undated (Box 8)
    - North Carolina mountain scenes, undated (Box 8)
    - Wisconsin, undated (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1920-1930, undated (Box 8)
    - A.S. Pearse, undated (Box 8)
  - Acid Free Envelopes
    - Identified people and places, ca. 1920-1959 (Box 8)
    - Unidentified places, undated (Box 8)
    - Unidentified people and groups, undated (Box 8)
    - New Orleans and Environs, undated (Box 8)
    - Woods Hole, Gloucester, Cape Cod, Mass, 1926, 1941, undated (Box 8)
    - Personal and Immediate Family, undated (Box 8)
  - Regular Slides
    - Large Box
      - Beaufort, 1958-1968 (Box 8)
      - Duke University Marine Laboratory, 1959 and undated (Box 8)
      - Massachusetts (W. Hole, Cape Cod, Plymouth), 1959-1960, undated (Box 8)
      - Hatteras Lighthouse, undated (Box 8)
      - Hatteras - Ocracoke, 1958 and undated (Box 8)
      - Puerto Rico, 1965 (Box 8)
      - Gulf of Mexico, Tuna Cruise, 1956 (Box 8)
      - Hurricane Donna, 1960 (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous, 1961-1966 and undated (Box 8)
    - Small Slide Boxes
      - Beaufort, 1958-1966 and undated, [5 boxes] (Box 8)
      - Hatteras - Dunes, 1959-1961 and undated (Box 8)
      - Hatteras, 1958-1959 and undated (Box 8)
      - Shackleford - Dunes, 1958-1963 (Box 8)
      - Outer Banks, 1961-1963 (Box 8)
      - Eastward Cruise, November 1965 (Box 8)
  - Glass Slides, including Beaufort, Hatteras, and Woods Hole, [2 boxes] (Box 8)